Guide to the
Brown University Library
Default Call Number
John Hay Library University Archives and Manuscripts Box A Brown University Providence, RI, 02912 Telephone: Manuscripts: 401-863-3723; University Archives: 401-863-2148 Email: Manuscripts: hay@brown.edu; University Archives: archives@brown.edu
Biographical/Historical Note
Collection information
There are no restrictions on access, except that the collection can only be seen by prior appointment. Some materials may be stored off-site and cannot be produced on the same day on which they are requested.
- La Cesnaye in Sorrow. Ferdinand de Lesseps Died in His Great Castle Yesterday.New York, NY, 1894 December 8; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page Inside front cover)
  Newspaper clipping from the New York Times of an obituary for the French diplomat Ferdinand de Lesseps, who died in Paris on December 7, 1894. Besides outlining his role in international diplomacy, the article emphasizes de Lesseps's role in constructing the Suez and Panama Canals.
  Lesseps, Ferdinand de, 1805-1894
- Ferdinand de Lesseps New York, NY, circa December 1894; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page Inside front cover)
  Newspaper clipping from a New York newspaper about Ferdinand de Lesseps, presumably published shortly after he died on December 7, 1894. The article underscores the corruption surrounding De Lesseps's project to construct the Panama Canal, which—the author asserts—overshadowed the man's earlier career achievements.
- The Talk of Paris New York, NY, 1894 December 26; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page Inside front cover)
  Newspaper clipping of an article published in the New York Evening Post on December 26, 1894 but written in Paris on December 14, signed with the initials "S.D." Column dedicated to several recent illustrious deaths currently being discussed in Paris. Most of the article is given to Ferdinand de Lesseps, recounting to his rise in the French foreign service, efforts to construct the Suez Canal, and his impressive physical stature as the well-known "grand Français." The article's final paragraphs also mention the deaths of Jean Macé and M. Burdeau. Macé was a long-time Republican Senator in France dedicated to the principles of liberalism and a popular writer of science books, most famously his History of a Mouthful of Bread. Burdeau was at one time the deputy of the French Chamber of Deputies. Attention is given to both Macé's and Burdeau's resistance to Socialism.
  Lesseps, Ferdinand de; Macé, Jean, 1815-1894; Burdeau, M.
- Ettlinger, John R.T. to Keeney, President of Brown University Providence, RI, 22671; 1 page; Ettlinger, John R.T. (Box 10, Volume 4, Page Inside front cover)
  Grants permission to temporarily remove the Universal Republican Alliance scrapbook of letters from the Annmary Brown Memorial to the Brown Photo Lab for microfilming.
  Keeney, Barnaby C. (Barnaby Conrad), 1914-1980
- Librarian's notes Providence, RI, 2 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page Inside front cover)
  Notes made at one point presumably by a librarian or cataloguer trying to keep track of which documents within the Universal Republican Alliance scrapbook had been assigned accession numbers. Page numbers are also listed for some items.
- Conseil Général and Coup d'État Marseille and Paris, France, 1849 November 12 - 21 December 1851; 6 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page Inside front cover)
  Several documents from French political meetings in 1849 and 1851. Contains first a program from the November 12, 1849 election for the position of conseil d'ètat, which lists the seven candidates: Colladon, Eugène; Cramer, ancien Syndic; Dufour, Général; Jacquier, Maire; Macaire-Prinsep; Montfalcon, Maire; and Odier-Cazenove. Also includes voting cards labelled "Oui" and "Non" from the vote held in Marseille on December 21, 1851 on whether or not to execute a coup d'état. An entrance ticket from a meeting of the National Assembly contains a hand-written note on the back stating that it was issued just one week before the 1851 coup d'état. These documents are all held together in an envelope containing a handwritten note about the Marseille vote.
- Volume description by Rush Hawkins, undated; 1 page; Hawkins, Rush C. (Rush Christopher), 1831-1920 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 0)
  Describes the contents of the volume: letters written by "several distinguised men – American, English and Italian," sent to Prof. L. Mariotti-Gallenga, "liberal patriot and autor of the history of Piedmont", in addition to documents pertaining to the Revolution of 1848 and 1849 in Rome and the "so-called French Revolution" under Napoleon III. Signed R.C.H.
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895
- To the European Committee L.S.B., 1867; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 1)
  Contains names and addresses of four men in London on the European Committee: T. Snowe, Esq. (editor of the "Observer" newspaper); P.A. Taylor, Esq. (Treasurer of the European Committee); Louis Bulewski, and a Mr. Marrini.
  Snowe, T.; Taylor, P.A.; Bulewski, Louis; Marrini
- The Republican Alliance, 1867 January 16; 16 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 2-16, plus one page tucked between pages 2 and 3)
  Handwritten copy of Giuseppe (here anglicized to "Joseph") Mazzini's "Republican Alliance," as read in an article published in the Atlantic Monthly in February 1867 and reprinted on January 16, 1867 in the New York Tribune. (Copy not in Mazzini's hand, but appears to be a study copy and includes underlining and capitalization of significant passages.) Tribune clipping is tucked between scrapbook pages. Mazzini writes on the occasion of the "peace now concluded" in the war for Italian unification, arguing that as long as Italy remains a monarchy, it is not fully independent of foreign rule. Only a republican national government can achieve the true liberation of a united Italian people.
  Ms 579 (1) and (2)
- To our friends in the United States London, England, 1865 December; 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Centre Revolutionnaire Europeen (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 17)
  Handwritten copy of Giuseppe (here anglicized to "Joseph") Mazzini's speech, "To our friends in the United States," written in London in 1865 to advocate for the United States to intervene in European politics and promote republican principles across the Atlantic. Signed by Mazzini and imprinted with the stamp of the "Centre Revolutionnaire Europeen, Londres." The speech was apparently delivered by envoy to the Friends of Republican Principles in America.
  Ms 580
- To the friends of Republican Principles in Europe New York, NY, 1866; 1 page; Stansbury, Edward Augustus, 1811-1873; Conkling, Frederick A. (Frederick Augustus), 1816-1891; Hawkins, Rush C. (Rush Christoper), 1831-1920; Tousey, Sinclair, 1818-1887; Cochrane, John; Friends of Republican Principles in America (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 18)
  Printed document circulated to members of the New York organization Friends of Republic Principles in America, containing a notice of a meeting in which members gathered to listen to an envoy read Giuseppe Mazzini's "To our friends in the United States." The circular contains a printed copy of Mazzini's address, in addition to a response drafted by a special committee (E.A. Stansbury, John Cochrane, F.A. Conkling, Rush C. Hawkins, and Sinclair Tousey) for the delegate of the European Republican Committee, Louis Bulewski, to bring back to London. Members of the organization are requested to sign the bottom of the circular so that their names may be added before the response is returned to Bulewski.
  Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Bulewski, Louis
- Bulewski's Proposal Washington, DC, 1866 March 9; 3 pages; Bulewski, Louis (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 19)
  Louis Bulewski, the envoy of the European Republican Committee to America, proposes a three-part plan to garner American support for European revolutionary efforts, after having spoken with members of the Friends of Republican Principles in America. Bulewski proposes: holding a meeting in New York to share public opinion about American dedication to republican principles and ideas about interventionism overseas; organizing a nation-wide committee dedicated to republicanism; and getting American aid for European republican press and propaganda.
  Ms 581
- The Universal Republic: Membership Pledge, 1866 August; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 20)
  Pledge form to be signed by members of the "Association" dedicated to helping found a Universal Republic around the world.
- Invitation to meet Louis Bulewski New York, NY, 1866; 1 page; Daly, Charles P. (Charles Patrick), 2826-2899; McKaye, James, 1805-1888; Cochrane, John; Hall, William A.; Tousey, Sinclair, 1818-1887; Friends of Republican Principles in America (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 21)
  Printed invitation to attend a gathhering to be held at the Loyal Republican Society in New York on April 19, 1866 to hear a report from Louis Bulewski, envoy of the Friends of Republican Principles in Europe, who is returning from Washington where he spoke with Congress about garnering American support for the Republican movement in Europe. Invitation is signed by Charles P. Daly, James McKaye, John Cochrane, William A. Hall, and Sinclair Tousey.
  Bulewski, Louis
- [illegibile] to McKay, James, Col. and associates Peterboro, NY, 1866 April 17; 2 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 22)
  Response to invitation to meeting in New York on April 19, 1866 to meet Louis Bulewski, envoy to America of the Friends of Republican Principles in Europe. The author of this letter will be unable to attend the meeting, but expresses ihs joy in the prospect of American and European collaboration in the "holy enterprise of ridding the nations of despots."
  Ms 582
  McKaye, James, 1805-1888
- Address to the Friends of Republican Principles in America, from the Friends of those Principles in Europe, with the Response Thereto.New York, NY, circa April 1866; 7 pages; Friends of Republican Principles in America (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 22-23, tucked between pages)
  Booklet printed by the Friends of Republican Principles in America. Contains: notice of April 1866 meeting in New York at which Col. F.A. Conkling was elected president, Col. Rush C. Hawkins was elected secretary, and Louis Bulewski read Giuseppe (here anglicized to "Joseph") Mazzini's address, "To our Friends in the United States"; the text of Mazzini's address; notice of the election of a committee of five to draft a response for Bulewski to bring back to London; and the text of the Americans' response "To the Friends of Republican Principles in Europe," including the names of all those who signed on to support the response. The list of supporters consists of fifty-two men from around the United States, including numerous U.S. Senators and Congressmen.
  Conkling, Frederick A. (Frederick Augustus), 1816-1891; Hawkins, Rush C. (Rush Christopher), 1831-1920; Bulewski, Louis
- Meeting held at 863 Broadway, April 19, 1866 New York, NY, 1866 April 19; 2 pages; Hawkins, Rush, C. (Rush Christophers), 1831-1920 (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 23-24)
  Handwritten minutes of the meeting of the Friends of Republican Principles in America held in New York on April 19, 1866. Signed by Rush Hawkins, Secretary.
  Ms 583 (1) and (2)
- Bulewski, Louis to My Dear Colonel and photograph of Bulewski, Louis New York, NY, 1866 June 7 or July 6; 2 pages; Bulewski, Louis (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 25)
  Informs "my dear colonel" (presumably Rush Hawkins) that E.A. Stansbury has requested to meet with him the next day. Date of letter is written numerically, either using American "month/day" or European "day/month" format. On the inside of the invitation is a photograph of Bulewski.
  Ms 584
  Hawkins, Rush, C. (Rush Christophers), 1831-1920; Stansbury, Edward Augustus, 1811-1873
- Bulewski, Louis to Sir London, England, 1866 July 31; 8 pages; Bulewski, Louis (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 26)
  Apologizies, presumably to Rush Hawkins, for the delay in an answer from the European Republican Committee about forming a "practical cooperative" with its American counterpart, but notes that before responding, the European committee wanted to see whether or not the current war in Europe between Bismark, Napoleon III, the Emperor of Russia, and "humiliated Italy" would "furnish a new yoke to the peoples of Europe." Proceeds with a lengthy overview of European political affairs and criticizes the military aggression of Prussia. Expresses the hope that at the very least, recent events would provide a fertile opportunity for Republican propaganda. Concludes with a firm call to the Friends of Republican Principles in America,, inviting them to prove whether or not they are "men of deeds."
  Ms 585 (1) and (2)
  Hawkins, Rush, C. (Rush Christophers), 1831-1920; Friends of Republican Principles in America
- Mazzini, Joseph to the New York Committee for the Universal Republican Alliance London, England, 1866 August 8; 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 27)
  After warning about the "divorce between thought and action" that has too often characterized contemporary affairs in which "many pledges have been broken" but expressing his faith that the New York Committee for the Universal Republican Alliance will make good on its promise to help the Universal Republican cause, Giuseppe (here anglicized to "Joseph") Mazzini celebrates the vision of world-wide republicanism, in which what were previously just local movements against depotism would be united in a cooperation binding Europe, the United States, and South America. Strong emphasis is placed on Mazzini's vision of republicanism as the epitome of Christian values: "Ours is a truly Holy Alliance, a highly religious fact," he writes: "the embodiment into a practical reality of the teacings of eigteen centuries of Christianity and of the aspirations of the great good and brave men of all times and countries, all pointing to One God and One Humanity." Mazzini goes on to outline three steps to bring about this universal alliance: the creation of a "continuous uninterrupted organization" with a clear structure; devotion to the Press, including the publication of a series of pamphlets entitled "Universal Republican Alliance"; and the raising of funds in America to support the European Republican Committee.
  Ms 586
  Friends of Republican Principles in America
- Stansbury, E.A. to Conkling, F.A., Col.New York, NY, 1866 August 17; 1 page; Stansbury, Edward Augustus, 1811-1873 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 28)
  Asks Conkling to share the enclosed letter from Louis Bulewski with John Cochrane and Sinclair Tousey, with the injuction to pass it on. Letter from Bulewski not present.
  Ms 587
  Conkling, Frederick A. (Frederick Augustus), 1816-1891; Tousey, Sinclair, 1818-1887; Bulewski, Louis; Cochrane, John
- Mazzini Proclamation to the Romans New York, NY, 1866; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 28-29, tucked between pages)
  Newspaper clipping from a New York Paper The London Star, containing the text of Giuseppe Mazzini's proclamation to the Romans, said to have been posted on the walls of Rome. In the proclamation, Mazzini criticizes the people of Rome for giving in to foreign monarchies rather than fighting for a united Italian republic. The article states that The London Star has testified to the authenticity of the text of the proclamation.
  Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872
- Universal Republican Alliance Subscription Notes: Prototypes, 2 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Universal Republican Alliance (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 29)
  Two hand-drawn designs for $20 subscription certificates to raise money for the Universal Republican Alliance. The top certificate contains the signature of Giuseppe Mazzini, anglicized to "J. Mazzini". The bottom certificate includes text in five languages and currencies: German, Spanish, Italian, French, and English.
  Ms 588 (1) and (2)
- The Universal Republic: Object and Form of Organization New York, NY, 1867 January; 1 page; Universal Republican Alliance (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 30)
  Typed document outlining the object of the Universal Republican Alliance ("to maintain the right of every Country to a Republican Government and the consequent duty of all Republicans to unite for a Solidarity of Republics") and hierarchical structure of the organization. Among other details, the document stipulates that all funds raised "for European work shall be placed at the disposal of Joseph Mazzini."
- Conkling, F.A. to Hawkins, Rush, Col.New York, NY, 1867 February 6; 2 pages; Conkling, Frederick A. (Frederick Augustus), 1816-1891 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 30)
  Conkling asks Hawkins to contact members of the American Committee of the Universal Republican Alliance to have them meet at Conkling's house. Includes the names of the five-member central committee.
  Ms 589
  Hawkins, Rush C. (Rush Christopher), 1831-1920; Tousey, Sinclair, 1818-1887; Stansbury, Edward Augustus, 1811-1873; Cochrane, John
- Hawkins, Rush to the London Committee of the Universal Republican Alliance (draft)New York, NY, 1867 February 20; 2 pages; Hawkins, Rush, C. (Rush Christophers), 1831-1920 (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 31-32)
  Responds to a letter sent to the New York Republican Alliance Committee by its London counterpart, agreeing to join forces across the Atlantic to promote the spread of republican ideals in Europe, but with certain caveats: "we regret exceedingly that our conditions may not be as favorable as you might have the right to expect." Includes reference to Americans' efforts to support current revolutionary uprisings in the Ottoman Empire.
  Ms 590 (1) and (2)
  London Committee of the Universal Republican Alliance; New York Republican Alliance Committee
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to [unidentified], 1867 March 27; 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 33)
  Handwritten copy of a letter from Giuseppe (here anglicized to "Joseph") Mazzini requesting monetary support from the United States to support the creation of an Italian republic. Among the elements at stake in the fate of Italian republicanism, Mazzini argues, is "liberty of conscience, the inviolability of the soul, proclaimed to all from the very place where it has been for so many centuries cancelled."
  Ms 591
- Obituary for William J. Linton, 1897 December 30; 1 Page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 34)
  Newspaper clipping of an obituary for William James Linton, an English-born engraver "intimately aquainted with [Giuseppe] Mazzini, [Giuseppe] Garibaldi, and Louis Blanc." Besides his engravings, Linton is also remembered for his literary pursuits. He spent much of his career in New Haven, CT, where he died.
  Linton, W.J. (William James), 1812-1897
- Linton, William J. to Hawkins, Rush New York, NY, 1867 April 17; 3 pages; Linton, W.J. (William James), 1812-1897 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 34)
  Linton sends Hawkins a copy of a document outlining the object and organizational structure of the Universal Republican Alliance and references Giuseppe Mazzini's requests for funding from the American Committee of the Universal Republican Alliance. He lends his support to the alliance and asks to attend meetings of the American Committee.
  Ms 592
  Hawkins, Rush, C. (Rush Christophers), 1831-1920; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Universal Republican Alliance
- Linton: Memorial Exhibition of His Works at the Century Association New York, NY, 1898 July 26; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 34)
  Newspaper clipping announcing an exhibit of some of the works of engraver and writer William J. Linton at the Century Association in New York City several months after his death.
  Linton, W.J. (William James), 1812-1897; Century Association (New York, N.Y.)
- With William James Linton: Poet, Engraver, Printer, and British Republican, 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 34-35, tucked between pages)
  Newspaper clipping published during William J. Linton's lifetime, describing his home in New Haven, CT. Particular attention is given to Linton's library, including "works of intimate friends, as Giuseppe Mazzini."
- Linton, William J. to Hawkins, Rush New York, NY, 1867 May 24; 2 pages; Linton, W.J. (William James), 1812-1897 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 35)
  Linton tells Hawkins that he will be soon leaving New York on a trip to England and asks for news about the $3,000 in subscriptions raised by the American Committee for the Universal Republican Alliance. Linton hopes that Hawkins will be able to get him the funds in time for him to bring to Giuseppe Mazzini, as help is very much needed for the "Roman movement." Second page contains stamp illustrating an image of three interlocking hands, a symbol associated with the Republican Alliance.
  Ms 593
- Linton, William J. to Hawkins, Rush New York, NY, 1867 May 25; 2 pages; Linton, W.J. (William James), 1812-1897 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 35)
  Clarifies a potential misunderstanding generated by Linton's letter of the previous day about the money raised by the American Committee of the Universal Republican Alliance for Giuseppe Mazzini.
  Ms 594
- Authors at Home: The Late William J. Linton in New Haven, 1898 January; 1 page; Linton, W.J. (William James), 1812-1897 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 35)
  Newspaper clipping of obituary for William J. Linton, with emphasis on his grand library and solitary lifestyle in a cottage just outside of New Haven, CT.
- Death List of a Day: William James Linton, 1898 December 30; 1 page; Linton, W.J. (William James), 1812-1897 (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 34-35, tucked between pages)
  Newspaper clipping of a short obituary for William James Linton.
- Universal Republican Alliance Subscription Notes, 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Universal Republican Alliance (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 36)
  Three printed subscription notes for the Republican European Committee of the Universal Republican Alliance in the amounts of 50 cents, $1, and $10. Contain signature of "Joseph Mazzini." Note that the funds are "redeemable by the First Republic established in Europe after the Issue."
- Everett, Edward to Mariotti, L.Boston/Cambridge, MA, 1838 February 27; 2 pages; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 37)
  Commends Mariotti for the quality of a certain lecture, the text of which he left for Everett to read. Promises to reach out to the Historical Society to inquire about having Mariotti deliver his lecture at one of their meetings. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 595
- Appleton, Many[?] to Mariotti, L.Boston/Cambridge, MA, circa 1838; 4 pages; Appleton, Many (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 38)
  Appleton reports on the difficulty of finding an audience for a series of lectures proposed by Mariotti, though he thinks he can procure ten auditors. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 596
- [illegible] to de Mariotti, Louis, "mio caro nipote"Parma, Italy, 1839 April 16; 3 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 39)
  Letter sent by one of Mariotti's relations in Italy while Mariotti was living in Cambridge, MA. The letter's writer news about a common acquaintance who had recently come to call on him. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 597
- Prescott, William H. to Mariotti, L.Boston, MA, 1839 April 22; 3 pages; Prescott, William Hickling, 1796-1859 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 40)
  Expresses his regret that Mariotti has decided to leave the Boston area to seek a position "on the other side of the water," presumably back in Europe. Prescott agrees to write Mariotti a letter of recommendation and thanks him for his insightful series of lectures on Italian literature delivered the previous winter. He commends Mariotti's linguistic skills and prowess as an educator. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 598